The incredible true story that defined our world.
The Professor and the Madman is a history, drama,
mystery film directed by Farhad Safinia.
Professor James Murray begins work compiling words for the first edition of the Oxford English Dictionary in the mid
19th century, and receives over 10,000 entries from a patient at Broadmoor Criminal Lunatic Asylum, Dr.
William Minor.
James Murray, played by Mel Gibson.
Dr. William Chester Minor, played by Sean Penn.
Eliza Merrett, played by Natalie Dormer.
Muncie, played by Eddie Marsan.
Ada Murray, played by Jennifer Ehle.
Charles Hall, played by Jeremy Irvine.
The Professor and the Madman is a 2019 biographical drama film
directed by Farhad Safinia (under the pseudonym P.
Shemran), from a screenplay by Safinia and Todd Komarnicki based on the 1998 book The Surgeon of
Crowthorne (published in the North America as The Professor and the Madman) by Simon Winchester.
It stars Mel Gibson, Sean Penn, Natalie Dormer, Eddie Marsan, Jennifer Ehle, Jeremy
Irvine, David O'Hara, Ioan Gruffudd, Stephen Dillane, and Steve Coogan.
The film is about professor James Murray, who in 1879 became director of an Oxford University Press project, The New English Dictionary
on Historical Principles (now known as the Oxford English Dictionary) and the man who became his friend and colleague, W.
Minor, a doctor who submitted more than 10,000 entries while he was confined at Broadmoor Criminal
Lunatic Asylum at Crowthorne after being found not guilty of murder due to insanity.
Shot in Dublin in 2016, the film became part of a legal battle between Gibson and Safinia against Voltage
Pictures, delaying its release until 2019 and resulting in the pair disowning the final product.
The film explores themes of based on novel or book, professor,
lunatic asylum, biography, based on true story.
The tone is intense and emotional and mind_bending.